[rock music]
[Peter] Bill, you're fourth generation.
You know it inside and out.
So we're gonna see it through your eyes.
[Bill] Memphis is a great place.
This is Main Street, it was once traffic
and then it got closed off
and made for pedestrian work only.
-So you have some stuff falling apart.
Businesses have moved out.
What was this before down here?
I mean, at one time when cotton was king,
this was the home of
massive amounts of business
and trading and organization.
After Martin Luther King's
assassination in '68,
Downtown Memphis became a ghost town.
It wasn't until like the late 80s
that reinvestment started back in downtown.
And the problem is
that 25 year dead period
created a lot of what
people think Memphis is,
which is not a crime ridden, nasty place.
-But on paper, it is one of the worst
homicide rates in the country.
It's gotten better.
-Yeah.
-Like most big cities right now.
But technically it is, right?
The statistics will tell you
annually it's one of the top five most
dangerous places in terms of violent crime.
You can't run from that fact.
That does not mean that people are
walking around getting mugged.
Like most crime,
it's people that know people.
The problem is,
as the city went through
its problems in the 70s and 80s,
poverty grew.
-Lack of access grew.
-Yep.
And because of the growth of those things,
crime followed it.
And the city hadn't gotten over it yet.
But it's working hard to do that.
People don't know the rich cultural,
musical business heritage.
This place was boarded up until 1984.
And it's where a local family
decided Downtown, Memphis
was reinvesting in.
And it's a South's Grand Hotel
called the Peabody,
started in the early 1900s
and shut down when downtown shut down.
And this became the anchor
for Memphis Revitalization
and it is one of
the finest hotels in the world.
-This is beautiful.
-And something you might want to know
is in the center of this place
is a fountain and there's ducks in it.
-Seriously?
There's reason there's ducks in it…
and they're trained to go upstairs
to the Duck Palace
and come down twice a day.
-The Duck Palace?
-Yeah.
It's on the roof.
-They live up there?
-They do.
And the reason it happened
is back in the 30s
some hunters brought some ducks back,
threw them in this thing…
-Oh yeah?
-Oh look.
-They're about to come down.
-[woman] Is this for the ducks?
I think so. Yeah.
Yeah, the ducks are coming down soon
and so all these people are here every day
to watch the march of the ducks.
-Mostly tourists, right?
I don't know where you from?
-We're from Wisconsin.
-Yes.
For Wisconsin
but there's some locals here for sure.
There's the Duck Commander?
-That's him!
-Hey, Duck Commander, say hello.
I'm Bill, fourth generation Memphian.
-Good to meet you.
-Good to see you.
-Hey, I'm Peter.
Peter has a show that reaches…
-How long you been doing this?
-Seven years.
-How's it going?
-Man, every day I wake up, it's a go.
Do you have
a good relationship with the Ducks?
I do. I get new Ducks every 90 days.
So it's my job to break them from being
a scared team that's unsure of themselves,
to where they're marching with such pride
that it's worthy of a red carpet.
And it's happening right now?
It's about to happen now.
Don't go nowhere.
I'm glad we bumped into you.
Completely by accident.
-I appreciate what you do for our city.
-I appreciate you.
So what happens is, Kenan,
who's the Duck Master,
will march the ducks down from the roof.
They will come down the elevator,
walk across the red carpet,
to much fanfare, swim around in the
fountain until the end of the afternoon,
and then they'll go home.
Oh, that's it, right?
[Bill laughs]
[Peter] The Duck Elevator. This is wild.
[Kenan] All right, duckies,
let's put some smiles on some faces.
Everybody say good morning, duckies!
[crowd] Good morning, duckies.
[applause]
And you know how Hollywood
has its walk of fame?
With the stars?
Memphis has its walk of fame,
and it's duck feet,
and its people who've mattered in Memphis.
All right, guys, the time has finally come
where we get to meet up in person.
The Your Fellow Americans book tour
kicking off early August.
New York, Boston, greater Detroit,
greater Chicago, greater Phoenix.
More locations coming.
You can buy your ticket here
with the QR code with your phone
or link down below in the description.
Here's what you get with the ticket.
You get a book.
You get a signed copy from me.
Your choice, handshake or high five.
And just a good time hanging out together
in the flesh and blood.
The biggest problem with video making is
I'm on this side of the screen
you're on that side,
and there's no interaction,
well, this is gonna change that.
It's gonna be a great celebration
for our country's birthday
with positive stories about the US
If you're not seeing your location,
I'm working on it.
It's the publisher
that comes up with the locations.
Really, that comes down to
the more tickets bought,
the more locations they're gonna add.
So, hey, if you want to help out
your fellow Americans,
those in the cities I mentioned,
and you're thinking of going,
you know, bring a friend,
bring a partner, bring whomever.
Purchase here or down here.
So looking forward to
meeting you in person.
Now back to Memphis.
[Bill] Memphians love to eat.
Best barbecue in the world.
Sorry, Texas. Sorry, North Carolina.
Sorry, the rest of you.
-It's the best.
-Okay. We'll try some later.
I'll judge it for you.
-We like to work. We like to hunt.
We like college football.
And we like to be entertained.
And one of the greatest places
to be entertained is Beale Street,
which is the home of
where rock and roll started.
Tina Turner, Elvis Presley,
Jerry Lee Lewis, B.B. King.
Just a couple of hours south is
the Crossroads, is the Mississippi Delta,
where the blues started.
And east of here
is where the old banjo
twangy rockabilly started.
And a very, very, very
heavy gospel influence.
-Right.
-And they collided in Memphis.
I never thought of the regional fusion
that made rock and roll.
Yeah. Nobody understands.
You got the blues from the Delta,
hillbillies coming in, gospel.
The church.
The deep, rich church gospel music.
And those three confluences
came together and created rock and roll.
[siren blares]
Main Street,
where we started, picks up here.
And it's a complete revitalization
of kind of a cool
entertainment arts district.
-I had no idea
Memphis would be so interesting.
Nobody does. You gotta get here.
This is a place
you're gonna rip by on I-40.
-Not worth stopping.
-It's too bad.
I'm not thinking of Elvis.
-I'm not a Graceland guy.
-All right.
Along the lines of that history
is our scar.
Our deep, deep, deep scar.
And certainly there's scars.
There's slavery, all kinds of scars.
But the greatest scar
is on April 4th, 1968, at 6:01 PM
Martin Luther King
was assassinated in our town.
That happened at the Lorraine Motel,
which has now been turned into
the National Civil Rights Museum.
-Oh, that's where it happened.
Right there.
-That's not only where it happened,
but where that wreath is is the balcony.
If you remember the iconic picture
of Jesse Jackson
shooting toward the shooter…
-…with Martin Luther King on the ground.
-Yep.
I'm gonna introduce you
to Jackie Smith, who was
the last resident of the Lorraine Motel
when this thing shut down
and turned into the museum,
who has been right here on the sidewalk
ever since 1987 and has not moved.
-Every day?
-Every day.
Where does she sleep?
Right there.
-Huh.
-Come on. Let me introduce you to Jackie.
Jackie!
-What you doing?
-Doing good. Thank you.
So good to see you. Meet my friend, Peter.
-Hey, Peter.
-Nice to meet you, Jackie.
-Oh, let me get my book.
-Okay. You get your book.
[Bill laughs]
Jackie's story is this…
She lived when the hotel
was not the museum, but just the hotel.
She was the last person to live here.
She locked herself in for 30 days
and wouldn't come out.
Because she believed
that the millions of dollars
that the city, county,
state, and federal government
were gonna spend
converting Lorraine  Motel into a museum
would better perpetuate
the memory of Dr. King
by making it a place
to help the disadvantaged.
And she locked herself in there
with cans of beans
and wouldn't come out for 30 days.
They finally removed her,
and they put all her stuff on the sidewalk.
She wants the story of Dr. King
not to be flashy
civil rights museum to the kids,
but action.
And so she is here today
and has been for the last 35, 40 years
to say, Dr. King wants action,
not monuments.
And that's what Jackie stands for.
-Jackie, you got Bill's book.
Oh, that's my book. She's in my book.
-Oh, you're in the book? Okay, cool.
He came out here early
when I started the protest.
He spent the night out here as well.
-Back in '86?
-Back in '86,
you couldn't walk down these streets.
Remember what Memphis was then, right?
-See that building down there?
-Yep.
Past the White Van.
There was hookers and everything
walking up and down through here.
And they put her stuff
out on the curb out there.
And I saw it on the news,
and I thought, why is this Black woman
protesting the Civil Rights Museum?
That doesn't make sense.
So I came down here to ask her.
And her story was so compelling, I spent
the night here with her a couple of nights.
Wrote a story about it,
and it ended up getting published
in Life or something.
I can't remember.
-Oh, cool.
I'm basically here in protest
against the exploitation of Dr. King
and the gentrification of this area.
You see, they've turned this area
into a very expensive community
where there's no affordable housing.
There's no affordable housing
for us to be in.
For the first 12 years,
I was able to spend the night here
after they evicted me from my room.
From the Lorraine Motel.
I was staying in room 301.
And so, in order for me to be here,
I had to have accommodations to be here.
So when they put me out I went
down the street and got one of those rooms.
And I could go back and forth
to the washroom,
take a break, clean up,
and that sort of thing up until 2000.
From 1988 to the year 2000,
I could do that.
And then, all of a sudden,
the landlord came and told me,
I've got to let that area go.
I have no such accommodations now.
And so now, that area has become
condominium, you see.
And so there's nothing affordable
in this area.
How  are you gonna have
a civil rights museum
surrounded by gentrification, you see?
-Did you know Dr. King?
-No, I did not.
I read Dr. King's books early on,
so I just educated myself
on his teachings and principles.
There have been people that have come here
from all walks of life,
school children,
various religions, all over.
So good to see you.
Buy yourself something to eat.
-Thank you. All the best.
-Jackie, take care. All the best.
He's one of the few
that's carried on the work.
-You love Bill?
-Absolutely. He's doing a great job.
-Thank you.
[Bill] I found two friends
that I drug with us.
-[woman] I just missed them.
-I knew you wouldn't mind.
-Here we go, guys. The Orpheum.
-The guy on the street is Peter.
-I assume so. Kristen. Nice to meet you.
-So good to see you.
And Peter, in true Memphis fashion,
we found friends.
-They're gonna come in with us.
-Yeah. At the Duck Walk.
How you doing, Kristen?
Okay. So, we have the Walk of Fame here.
Walk of stars.
They're gonna see Jerry Seinfeld tomorrow.
-Seinfeld comes here tomorrow?
-Yes.
Oh, fantastic.
-This building's been here,
it'll be 100 years in 2028.
[Bill] Coming to the South's finest theater
that if you sat down on Broadway,
it would not look out of place.
[Kristen] Thank you.
So, this is our new season
that we just announced.
[Peter] Oh, wow. This is beautiful.
-There has been a theater
at this spot since 1890,
but the building we're standing in
right now has been here since 1928.
-I'll let you take it all in.
-[Peter] It is grand.
You're not gonna see a lot of places
that have gold leaf, crystal chandeliers.
-Oh, wow. Look at that balcony.
Even the wide angle can't get it all in.
-[Bill] Would you think this is in Memphis?
-No.
-Nobody does.
-No. This is happening.
So, do you guys pack this place out?
Oh, yes. So, we're 2,300 seats.
We have a performance tomorrow.
Our bread and butter is we bring
touring Broadway productions
about eight times a year.
But, of course, in between,
we have comedy, concerts, dance companies.
-So, you're pretty fired up working here?
-Oh, yes.
I'm a Broadway nerd
that gets to do what she loves every day,
which is introduce Broadway to Memphis.
Which Memphis, I love.
I'm a born and raised Memphian.
And then introduce Memphis
to the shows that I love.
-Okay. As a born and raised Memphian…
-Yes.
-You love your city?
-I love my city.
Why?
-I love it because she's real honest
with herself, sometimes to a fault.
I think sometimes
we're really hard on ourselves.
But Memphis is home. Memphis is family.
My entire family is here.
And honestly, with me working here
I always said I would leave
if I ever got bored.
But things are happening, growing,
changing at the Orpheum in Memphis,
-So I love being here
-She's hard on herself. What do you mean?
Memphis can be really critical
'cause we've let other people
be critical of us without knowing us.
And so I think we can equally
be as hard on ourselves.
-You've let other people write your story?
-Yeah.
Absolutely.
I feel very honored
to be able to work where I do
in this crown jewel of Memphis.
-This is stunning
as someone that loves architecture…
-We're also one of
the most haunted places in Memphis.
-You feel the haunted vibes here?
-I haven't had any experiences,
but I've had some colleagues
have some experiences,
and so I have to trust their experience.
But that box right there is known to house
one of our most famous ghosts, Mary.
-She's a 12-year-old ghost.
-Up here?
Okay, right here. Guys, do you see Mary?
-[Bill] What's the story?
-Coming through the screen?
She was hit by a trolley car
outside the Orpheum,
and she was brought inside,
and she loved it so much, she stayed.
And so she's a mischievous ghost.
Thankfully, we don't have any
malevolent spirits.
They're happy to be here. [laughs]
[Peter] You know what
I don't see in Memphis?
People set up on the streets,
other than Jackie.
-Who seems like she's grandfathered in.
-She's a fixture.
But I'm just saying,
I don't see people that…
1,200 philanthropies
in the city of Memphis do.
-Which isn't always good.
People have a place to go.
People have a place to go in many cities.
People in Skid Row want to be on fentanyl,
don't want to go to those places,
'cause then they can't do fentanyl.
Here, they must be enforcing it, as in,
you don't have the option
to stay on the street, right?
We don't have the police breaking up camps.
You also don't see cops, do you?
I don't. I haven't seen a cop.
I hear a lot of sirens, I'm not gonna lie.
Near my place at night,
there was a lot of sirens,
but I have not seen
any officers walking anywhere.
No, it's…
I'm just telling you, it's not a problem.
It's not a big issue here.
There are so many churches downtown.
We have more churches in Memphis
than we have gas stations.
Are people going to church?
Well, the churches do outreach programs
where they have places for people to eat
and to sleep, and the homeless
tend to congregate in those areas.
What about the Memphis Task Force
and the National Guard?
A lot of people will know about that
'cause it hit mainstream media.
The National Guard is window dressing.
What the Task Force is,
is 17 entities
from the federal government
all the way from Customs to the FBI
to the Attorney General's Office
that came to Memphis about six months ago
to work with the city
to round up
its most dangerous felonious activity.
All right?
This is a Democrat city.
This is the largest minority-majority city
in the United States, believe it or not.
Not Atlanta, Memphis.
And while policy-wise,
there may be a lot of people
in government positions municipally
that don't align with,
especially ICE and some other stuff,
we can all agree
we needed help fighting crime.
And so…
much to the city government's credit,
instead of fighting it,
they said, look, it's inevitable.
We can't keep the federal government
from coming here and doing work.
But what we can do is we can fight it
and we can have riots and the stuff
you've seen on TV in some other cities,
or we can at least sit down at the table
and find places where we can agree.
And if we can do that
and build a relationship with each other,
while we're not gonna support some of it,
we can support part of it and get along.
And at least we know what's going on.
And so that's the way
Memphis approached all of it.
And as a result,
crime is down this year.
Violent crime is down, I think 42%.
-Oh, wow.
-We've had some very non-violent protests
against ICE, specifically.
But beyond that,
I think by and large,
the city has embraced
the fact that some FBI guys
are rounding up felons
and the Highway Patrol
and the US Marshal Service interacting
with the Memphis Police Department
to get the worst off our streets.
-So are most people for it
or it just depends who you talk to?
Oh, you know,
that's a hard question to answer
because I don't know that it's been polled.
And if it has, I don't know the polls.
But I would tell you
across racial and political spectrums,
Black, White,
progressive, Democrat, whatever,
the vast majority of people that I talk to,
will say there's good and bad
but the good outweighs the bad.
Okay.
And if it makes our city safer
and a better place to do business
and a better place to go out to eat
and a better place to be entertained
and a better place for our children,
then I'll grin and bear
some of the parts I don't like
for the good parts that have helped us.
And I really do think that's probably
the prevailing attitude toward it all.
Gotcha.
This is getting down near
the Mississippi, right?
Yeah. It's the river. This is front.
It's typically considered
a business district.
AutoZone was founded
by Pitt Hyde here in Memphis.
And it's one of our bigger
publicly traded Memphis companies.
They've invested and their
world headquarters is Downtown, Memphis,
which is right here on your left.
-Oh, there. Yep.
-Very nice facility.
And what's neat is it's a confluence
of the old and new
'cause you see all the old
architecture from…
-Yeah, this is great.
The first revival of the city
mixed with the new architecture
from today's revival.
The Cotton Museum is
the Cotton Exchange Building on the right.
That's where 80% of the world's cotton
was traded for many decades.
-Okay. Out of this Art Deco beauty?
-That's Cotton Exchange Building.
That's like the New York
Stock Exchange of cotton.
-Okay.
-Across the street
used to be a parking garage.
That is now the new Brooks Museum,
which you could put that thing
in New York or Chicago or LA
and it would fit in just fine.
-What kind of museum is it gonna be?
-Art.
But what's amazing about it
is the floor plan.
It's open and they're using
as homage to Memphis,
all kinds of hardwoods in it.
White oak flooring, locust walls.
It's gonna have a massive promenade
out the backside overlooking the river.
And then the top is an open air
gathering area on top of the museum.
We've had people from,
I think, Switzerland.
I know New York,
have come to see this thing being built.
-It's huge.
-All the natural wood products.
It's huge and very, very, very impressive.
This was the custom house.
It was the customs office for
when people came into our country
up the Mississippi River.
It was originally
US Customs and Border Patrol.
It is now
the University of Memphis Law School.
-A lot of immigrants
were coming up the Mississippi.
-And their first touch on land was here?
-Lots.
Some of those immigrants
were unfortunately slaves.
-Right, right, right, right.
So this was the customs house
that cleared both…
-Oh, you're talking
all the way from Africa?
Yes. Well, and the Caribbean.
-Wow.
-Yeah.
So New Orleans is the point where
the Mississippi River enters into the Gulf.
And you follow it up.
And your next big stop
is Vicksburg, Mississippi.
Then your next hub
was Memphis and then St. Louis.
This is the trail.
-Bill, where's all the money coming from
for a museum like that?
-That's huge dollars.
-100% private donations.
-So there's that much money
kicking around this town?
There's a lot of old money in this town.
But most importantly, the old money cares.
The old money wants to get Memphis back
to what it rightfully should be.
There are people fighting to bring it back
from what it went through
in the 60s and 70s.
The reason it's called Memphis, it's on
the river like Memphis, Egypt on the Nile.
That's where it got its name.
So some time ago, someone decided
we should build a pyramid
because it's Memphis.
So this was actually
where the University of Memphis
and the Grizzlies played.
-It was a sports arena.
-Okay.
And it was the Memphis Pyramid.
It's on the river.
And anyway, it became outdated.
It was really hard to outfit
for more seats.
And believe it or not,
Bass Pro bought the thing.
And it's now the largest
Bass Pro in the United States.
But what's interesting is
inside the bottom of it,
you're walking through
a massive zoo aquarium.
There's alligators and massive fish.
-No way.
-Oh, it's incredible.
And inside it is the largest
freestanding elevator in North America
that takes you to the tip top of that.
You can get out there and watch.
And inside that glass thing up there
is some massive four-story aquarium.
That's like 30 feet in diameter,
full of all kind of catfish and stuff.
And it's very cool.
Not only four miles
from all of the things you just saw
are also neighborhoods that are
in dire need of investment and repair.
And the city is working on it.
But it is where my players
from Manassas came from.
-It is…
-Okay, just to explain that.
-You were a high school football coach.
-Yeah.
You made a fantastic documentary.
I was minding my own business
coaching football.
And two dudes that looked like you with
skinny legged jeans, they wore scarves.
-Are they skinny?
-Yeah, they had hair.
But they wore scarves, showed up from LA,
and followed us around and made a movie
that we thought we'd see on Channel 522
at 3:00 AM one Wednesday night.
And it went big.
And yeah, 10 months later
I'm walking down the red carpet
at the Academy Awards
and it won an Oscar.
-Back in 2011?
-Yeah. It's called Undefeated.
And it was about me coaching football.
And the movie's not about football,
it's a human interest story.
-It's so good.
[Bills voice] The character of a man
is not measured in how he handles his wins
but what he does with his failures,
and tonight we failed.
And everybody says
when you get these inner city kids down,
they'll lay over
and you'll beat them by 40.
Not us!
You walk with your chins up.
I am proud to be a Manassas Tiger
on this field tonight
'cause my guys didn't lay down.
They got heart.
Now let's put our mind
with our heart and our bodies.
And let's finish this thing this year.
Those kids that I coached at Manassas
are also part of the Memphis story.
And the work that we've done downtown
and continue downtown to bring it up,
same in midtown
that we'll show you in a little while.
We have to have the same level
of care and concern
for the most disadvantaged
among us that exist in Memphis.
And I think it's important
to see all sides of a cube.
-Yep.
And part of the Memphis cube is
we still have a lot of work to do.
And where it came from largely
has to do with the White flight
that started after the King assassination
and busing in the early 70s.
-So White flight happened because crime
ticked up and families of means were like,
-"I don't want to raise my kids in this."
-Some of that's right.
And also some of it's because White people
were scared of Black children.
I mean, it's just true.
I don't want my White kids
to go to school with Black kids.
-When integration was happening?
-Yes. That's busing.
When you take kids
out of an all-Black community
and bus them to an White community
and you take kids out of a White community
and bus them to an all-Black community
in the name of integration,
that sounds right.
But the people with wealth,
they just take their ball and go home.
The people without wealth that don't
like that plan, they've got no options.
And so what happens is
you end up with White flight
and all of the resources and access
that goes along with business ownership
and everything else that leave
and it creates an access desert.
A lot of people talk about
food deserts, academic deserts.
I call it access deserts.
You have two or three generations of that,
and you end up with blight.
You end up with schools
not having private investment
and PTA clubs and booster clubs.
And you end up with disenfranchisement
and gangs and crime
fills the vacuum.
It's two tales of one city,
instead of a tale of two cities.
Part of the Memphis story
is a story of loss.
While we still have FedEx,
and International Paper, and AutoZone,
and Terminex, and ServiceMaster,
and a lot of great companies,
we lost Firestone.
We lost Caterpillar.
We lost Northwest.
We were a Northwest hub.
And when Delta bought them,
we lost our hub.
And every time one of those things lose,
goes with it,
good blue-collar jobs typically.
-Firestone Dental,
so you can see the footprint of it here.
Oh, you're about to
really see the footprint.
This is what is called New Chicago.
Once, up until the 70s,
an extremely proud
Black neighborhood.
Isaac Hayes went to high school here.
Great schools, great everything.
This 170 acres to our left
was the second largest
Firestone plant in the United States.
-Okay.
And when it left,
all of these businesses on the right…
-You see these abandoned smokestacks?
-Yep.
It wasn't just Firestone.
It was all the smaller industries
around Firestone that supported Firestone.
It's like if you got a Ford Motor Company,
you've also got a seat manufacturer
and a bolt manufacturer.
And Firestone leaves,
you leave all these others.
These were massive industrial complexes
employing thousands of people.
Look how all the way back
to the power grid.
-All the way back there?
-We've been driving a mile.
That was one Firestone plant.
-Okay.
So this part of town was thriving.
-50s, 60s?
-It was. Absolutely. Blue collar, thriving.
Grocery stores, restaurants,
businesses, housing.
-No food desert at that time?
-No. It was great.
But the problem is
the people who can afford to be mobile,
they leave.
They vote with their wallet and their feet.
-Just like anyone would.
Just like anyone would.
The people who can't,
who don't have mobility,
who don't have that access
to mobility, they stay.
And then three generations later,
we wonder why their kids are in gangs
and not doing well in school.
Well, what have they had access to
other than loss?
What have they had access to
other than blight?
Right?
And there has not been enough investment.
And when I say investment,
there's all kinds of 501(c)
and all that stuff that spend money.
I'm talking about real investment.
Investment in the people.
Investment in the education.
-Similar tale in other parts
of the country, you know?
You can go deep into Appalachia,
into West Virginia, right?
The coal jobs, a lot of them have left.
Things are down and out.
But dude, this is gangland.
This is gangland?
Oh, this is gangland.
And I say that without hesitation
because I can point at houses
where my former players lived.
I've been all over these streets
rounding up kids.
O.C. Brown from the movie?
That's his grandmama's house,
the yellow one.
-Yeah, that's the guy in your movie.
You guys got to see the documentary.
It's so cool.
-This house right here
is where one of my tailbacks lived.
They were brothers, Mark and Larry.
Jamie Bobo lived around the corner.
But if you look,
these are for the gotten people.
-But look at that right there.
-Yeah.
New playground, right?
-Yeah, there was a couple of kids
killed there not long ago.
-Oh, geez.
-Gunfire.
Notice that there's nobody in it.
You can build a park all you want
but that's not investing.
-But money isn't the solution.
-No.
It's part of it, but it's not the solution.
We got to invest in the people, education.
-So how does it feel for you
coming through here?
-Just kind of like old home week.
It hadn't changed.
This is what it looked like 20 years ago.
And look at them.
They're planting something.
It's a neighborhood garden.
They're gonna be growing vegetables.
So it takes everyone in the community
and that's the hard part.
That's why it's so complicated
because you got to go with the kids.
Most people my age are not changing.
Right? It's just, let's be honest.
So you got to go with the kids.
But then to give the kids the best chance
they need good parents.
So that does also mean
you have to go at parental advice.
Do you know what the data says
about reading proficiency?
-It's pretty bad right now, right?
Here's the data.
If you don't read
on grade level by third grade
you are 70% more likely to be locked up
and divorced than someone who does
read on grade level by third grade.
So then you take an area like this
where tons of single parent households
are working all kinds of shifts.
Kids aren't being read nighttime stories.
They aren't being sung lullabies.
And by and large,
their parents weren't either.
What you find is
you find a huge literacy gap
that starts the downhill boulder
that the data says
you can do all the work you want to
when people are 21 years old.
-But the damage has been done.
-Yeah.
We have to invest in the schools.
We have to invest in early education.
We have to invest in…
This is piggyback on what you said.
You're right.
People our age aren't gonna do anything.
We've got to invest in these kids
so they can change this for themselves.
We don't need to be paternalistic
and tell everybody
what they need for their neighborhoods.
We've got to invest in the children
in their neighborhoods.
In the literacy programs, in business,
and let them work on
their own neighborhoods.
-Here's the reality too, Bill.
I'm all over the country.
You know who I'm meeting a lot of
these days? What demographic?
Former teachers that aren't that old.
They're not at retirement age.
They're getting out of the profession. Why?
It's gotten really hard. Why?
Because they can't discipline like
they need to to keep class in order. Why?
What support
are they getting from the parents?
Exactly.
And so the parents aren't doing their work.
Many of them at home.
And so they drop their kids off.
And then drop
a chaotic situation on the teachers
and the teachers can't do anything.
And they're like, you know what?
Why am I doing this?
And they're leaving.
A lot of good teachers.
-Yeah.
-So the problem goes deep.
And we're not gonna have the solution.
-What is this?
-I have no idea.
Let's go check this out.
[Peter] How you guys doing?
-You got a trucking school out here?
-Yeah.
-You guys are all getting your licenses?
-Yes.
-So you do your training right here?
-Yes, sir.
-You're gonna truck?
-Yeah. I'm 19 years old.
-19, you ready to hit the open road?
-Yes, sir.
Nice.
It's a good way to see the country, right?
For sure.
-Get paid to travel.
-See new things, too.
Okay. What's the pay right now
if you get a good gig,
cross-country trucking?
Best case scenario, what can you make?
-$100,000.
-$100,000?
-Yeah. $100,000 a year.
-Nice.
How is it right now
instructing the young guys?
It's rewarding watching people changing.
-So it's a great opportunity?
-For sure.
It could be life-changing.
Within two years,
you can get $100,000 a year trucking.
And you're not spending much, right?
Living on the road?
That depends if you drive
for a company or you own and operate
If you own and operate you gonna be
responsible for all your own expenses.
Insurance.
Your authority.
All the repairs on your truck.
But if you drive for somebody else,
you just drive.
-You guys all grew up in Memphis?
-Yeah.
-Do you love your city?
Love it?
You weren't scared to
just come out here and pull up like this?
-I'm not. Should I be?
Nah.
No? I go everywhere.
I've been in the hoods
of Karachi, Pakistan, Saudi Arabia, Iran.
I just feel it out. If I felt a bad vibe,
I would have went the other way.
Don't look at the stereotypes.
You just got to be here to see it.
Take care of you guys.
Those guys are great.
I knew you'd love those guys.
They're calling you
a crazy White boy right now.
Yeah. They said, weren't you scared
to come over? I just feel it out.
If I felt a bad energy, I would have
turned the other way but I didn't.
There's nothing to be scared of.
They're just people.
At first they're like, who's the White cop
looking dude with a camera?
-Yeah.
-And you have to sort of prove yourself.
But it's cool. So those guys,
they're getting their CDL licenses.
Right.
So you're coming out of here
potentially making 100K.
-It's huge.
And I don't want to get dark with this,
but I'm just gonna say what I feel.
-Yeah.
Imagine the day when
automated trucking just takes over.
You know, when that day comes.
Maybe there's another opportunity
but that one's gonna close down
for guys like this here.
I wonder and worry about a lot of that too.
Think how many people make a living
driving a taxi and an Uber.
-Yeah.
-All of it.
You were literally two miles from
where we were just at.
-Different universe.
-A different universe.
-The Orpheum and here.
Literally two miles from each other.
The hood is pretty big in Memphis?
-The hood is big in Memphis.
-Both on north and south side?
You got to think of Memphis geographically.
If you go west, you're in Arkansas.
Well, you're the river, right?
If you go south, you're in Mississippi.
So we're in the very southwestern most
corner of Tennessee.
So the only place to go is north and east.
As you think about the city,
the downtown's the center.
Then the central of the city
is midtown out through East Memphis.
The hoods are South Memphis
and North Memphis.
So the hoods surround the city corridor.
Geographically, that's how it works.
Now, you cannot…
you simply cannot tell the story of Memphis
without including St. Jude Hospital.
St. Jude Hospital
was founded by Danny Thomas,
who back in the 50s and 60s
was a megastar, right?
Danny Thomas talk show, Danny Thomas this,
Sammy Davis Jr.,
Danny Thomas, all those guys.
He's from Memphis.
He started out on a quest
to cure childhood cancer.
Back when children who got cancer,
92 or 93% of children died.
That number is now like 17%.
And he started St. Jude Children's
Research Hospital for Cancer Research,
which is these pink buildings
are part of the campus.
-Okay, those two big buildings?
That's two of them.
The campus is now 60 acres.
It is the leading
children's research hospital in the world.
And nobody pays a dime.
-No way.
-We have children in Memphis
from all over the world
with the rarest,
sickest type of childhood cancers.
And they come here
and their lodging, their care,
zero dollars.
-Who's paying for it?
-Donations.
It's a private entity.
-So donations are paying
the doctors' salaries?
-And this entire campus
that goes down three blocks.
-Whoa.
All of what you see is St. Jude.
-This comes right out of the hood.
You were just in the hood.
You were in the hood a minute ago.
And now look.
-Okay, so this…
This is the reinvestment
in Memphis I'm talking about.
-Look at this place.
-Yeah, that's crazy.
Dude, do you understand?
They are treating 600 children right now
for the rarest forms
of childhood cancer known to mankind.
And nobody that is in that hospital
is paying a dollar for that care.
And they, St. Jude's,
every time they make a breakthrough,
they don't try to publicize it
or keep it as their own.
They share 100% of all of their research
with every children's hospital on earth.
-How does one get their kid in there?
You call and say, my kid's got cancer
and if they've got a bed, you're in.
And there's kids here from Argentina,
from Ukraine, from Memphis.
There's kids here from all over the world.
Okay, but check this out. The
opportunities are right next to the hood.
Yes. All over the place.
-They're not out in the middle of nowhere.
-No!
A high-paying job
is literally out the door.
-Look at all this development.
-No, but hear me out, Bill.
-But if you're not educated on how to work…
-Exactly.
That's what I was trying to get at.
You can literally walk out your door
to a high-paying job,
but if you don't have the skills,
you're not making it.
And some guy from India
is flying in and working there.
Yes.
[Bill] It is unbelievable.
Everything you see is the hospital.
And people cross the bridge,
drive past it every day, and have no idea.
-I had no idea.
So, as we kind of transfer out of downtown,
heading east toward what we call midtown,
it's still the same vibe.
The center corridor is full of development.
The north and the south
need continual work.
One of the more iconic places in Midtown
is up here on your left,
which is Sun Studios.
Which is Jerry Lee Lewis, Roy Orbison,
Elvis Presley, B.B. King.
Johnny Cash recorded his albums here.
No way.
Yeah, that's Sun Studios.
That's where all of that music was made.
Right there.
The home of blues
and rock and roll is Memphis.
And the home of country is Nashville.
-Tennessee is responsible
for so much music. Isn't that crazy?
for so much music.
-I never thought about it like that.
-It's true.
-This is Overton Square. Pretty cool area.
-Okay.
This was the first place in Tennessee
you could buy liquor by the glass.
And a place you may have heard of,
where the very first one
was right here where this balcony was.
It was an interesting place
and they didn't know what to name it until
a guy got a drink by a glass and said,
"Thank God it's Friday."
-TGI Fridays.
-Yeah.
-Right there.
-Okay. There you go.
This is now what's considered Midtown,
but in the 20s,
this was the outskirts, right?
Only three miles from here
is the third most dangerous zip code
in the United States.
-Yeah. That's wild.
-Right.
But this is called Central Gardens,
which was the first kind of affluent
development outside of downtown.
It is still very, very well regarded.
Beautiful houses, antebellum.
There's a lot of energy here
in terms of keeping the neighborhood up
and pretty and well maintained.
-So what are people doing for work here now
to afford these places?
Or it's just old money?
-We still have a massive banking community.
Still huge in transportation.
There's tons of industry in Memphis still.
-Okay. How much are some of those homes
we just passed, roughly?
-Here? A million dollars.
$800,000 to a million.
You go down here
and they're a $1.5, $2 million.
-Okay.
-So it's pretty stately.
Beautiful old trees in here.
And kids walk to school here.
Still ride their bikes to school.
You know, this big, bad, dangerous area
where our kids walk to school.
-So when these people see on the news,
like, Memphis is failing…
These are people
that are digging in and investing.
These people could live in the suburbs.
They can buy anything
they want to in the suburbs.
But they choose to put down roots
and support their community.
-Well, and also the suburbs
aren't gonna make a home like this.
No. But there are some suburbs
that are pretty insanely nice.
-Okay. So the big, big money of Memphis,
where is it?
-It's in the center of the city,
out through the suburbs.
All right, guys. Bill had to take a call,
so I got a few minutes to walk around here
just to show you what it's like.
These absolutely
stunningly beautiful homes.
How you doing, man?
Ladies beware?
Yeah.
Not guys. [laughs]
Yeah, guys. So when you go down
streets like this in Memphis,
which there are actually more of them
than I thought there would be,
it's just, I don't know what? Mayberry?
Really blissful, nice, beautiful.
Things well taken care of, obviously.
And then you saw the other side
of the tracks
and the story for that, right?
Firestone going out of business
and the companies that went with it.
It's a complicated city
for being under a million people.
It's still, you know,
substantial size, over 600,000.
And I'm sure there are
some middle class neighborhoods
that are in between what we've seen today.
But this just goes to show you,
easy labels are just that, easy labels.
And when you dig into a place,
things are always more complicated,
nuanced, and I'd say interesting
once you start tapping in,
because Memphis is one of those
underdog places
that you go in thinking it's gonna
not be like this.
And then when you get into
these parts of the town, you're like, wow,
it's really a pleasant surprise.
-We watch your videos.
-You watch my videos?
-Yeah.
-Thank you.
I saw you and I was like, "Oh my God."
-Yeah. I'm making a video on Memphis.
-It's pretty cool.
-Yeah. It's a nice city.
But with all the voting stuff
going on right now,
-The gerrymandering, like they…
-Okay. They're doing that here?
-Yeah. It's like they split up
because we're like the only Democratic…
-…like congressional district.
-Sure, yeah.
They just split it up.
So that's like a big…
-I hate that.
When I lived in California,
what they did there, they took
this district in the far northeast,
which is basically ranchers,
connect that all the way down
to Marin County,
which is just north of San Francisco.
Which is gonna vote Left.
So it's not representative
of those people up there.
And I just feel like
everyone's playing this dirty game.
-Yeah.
-I hate it.
I don't know how it's allowed in our system
because it takes people's power away.
Yeah.
And especially in a state like Tennessee.
-Where it's majority Republican, obviously.
-Yeah.
But like Memphis and Nashville
are majority Democrat.
And especially in a city like Memphis
where it's majority Black.
Yeah.
And like it's just underrepresented and
it was gonna be a big like congressional,
I guess the elections this year, next year.
Okay. Yep.
I mean, I'm only 17.
So I'll vote next year.
-Yeah.
-But you don't want to see this.
Yeah. This is bad for our city.
People talk bad about the city,
like LeBron James, you just saw.
-I didn't know.
-He was talking bad about Memphis.
-Why? Is he from here?
-No, he's not even from here.
He's just saying
it's the worst place to come play.
There's nothing to do,
which gave a sense of like city pride.
Yeah. From the outside,
it's way cooler than I thought it would be.
You live here, Tom. You're from Memphis?
-I'm from…
-Okay. How is it?
What's your take on the city?
Well, it's a, it's a fun place to be
is all I can tell you.
It's been good to me and I love it.
You're a drummer?
I'm a drummer and this town…
Matter with your finger
that it's got that hair on?
Yeah. I just I'm getting at that age
where like the ears get bigger and.
-You need to see a doctor.
-Trim nose hair, you know.
But this is…
-It's serious. Yeah.
-It's serious.
Okay. So look, yes, I'll be serious here.
-No, don't.
-I won't be able to do it.
Yes. I'm a musician. I play drums
and I've been playing in this town
for 50 or 60 years.
I'm not gonna say how many.
And it's afforded me a fun lifestyle.
I'll put it that way.
Jazz drummer?
I'm a jazz drummer primarily,
but I play everything.
I play country. I play in a brass band.
I'm in a couple of jazz trios.
I do recording.
-What's your take on the city?
Memphis, let's just call a spade a spade.
It has a bad reputation, unfortunately.
Here's what it is, man.
There's bad things everywhere
in the world.
I don't care where you went.
You're gonna find some negative business.
You can either deal with that or you can
work around it and go your way.
So I believe that's what you do in life.
And therefore,
Memphis is a beautiful place.
Great weather. Great people.
Everybody's friendly. It's easy.
It's not a hassle.
We've got our issues and things.
But, you know, we deal with,
for instance, race.
Let's just talk about race.
We deal with it
better than most people, most places.
We've been dealing with it
a lot longer than most cities.
And I play in bands that are integrated,
and it's wonderful.
It's just absolutely wonderful.
We all accept each other
and love each other
just like anybody else.
So all of that and, you know,
economics and all that.
-Every city's got that, man.
-Yeah.
And then Stella
is who hooked me up with you.
-Stella the neighbor.
-Stella's a neighbor.
And what a friendly, fun neighbor she is.
She's got a great brain.
She's in the honor society.
She's gonna be graduating next year
and going to, what's it, Yale?
-Maybe if I'm lucky.
-If she's lucky.
Some college where she will further
her education and learn that
she probably shouldn't have gone to college
anyway, but that's something you do.
Because when you get out…
You've got to learn how to do
whatever that was.
But it's gonna be great.
And Chris has been the best neighbor ever.
-That's Stella's father.
-Oh.
Chris and I sit on the porch
and chew the fat.
-Do you?
-Yeah.
He's a fun man to chew it with.
During COVID, Tom would put on
porch concerts for the whole neighborhood.
He is very generous with his art.
We'd have people
setting up chairs out here.
It was the first music I saw during COVID.
It was like an oasis in the desert.
Well, that's beautiful right there, man.
Designed to heal you up.
-You know what I learned today?
-What did you learn today?
-Tell me your name again.
-Peter.
-I don't know why I didn't put it together.
-What?
Music out of Memphis is really a fusion
of the Delta, the blues of the Delta,
the folk of the sticks of Tennessee.
-And then gospel.
-Oh.
-Smashing together.
-That's what makes it good.
It's a confluence.
-And then rock and roll came out of that.
-And look where we are.
We're right in between Mississippi,
Arkansas, and Tennessee.
So all these rural farms that used to be
plantations and whatever,
all these people would come to Memphis on
the weekends and hang out on Beale Street
and bring their songs
and their stories and their business
and swap ideas and make it happen.
And that's still going on.
Maybe it's not quite like that now,
but the interaction is amazing.
-Your music scene is still happening here?
-Oh, yeah.
-A lot of live music?
-Uh-huh.
That's probably 25 venues a night
in the city that plays music.
-Are you serious?
Maybe not on Monday and Tuesday nights,
but on other nights, yeah.
-You've made your life as a musician here?
-Isn't that incredible?
And can you live in
a nice neighborhood like this?
Yeah, but now I was smart with the money.
You're doing my dream.
I always wanted to play the drums.
Why wouldn't you just do it, Peter?
Yeah, 'cause I'm doing this,
I'm talking to you.
Look here. Life is that long. Okay?
Go get a drum set.
Everybody needs one.
Hey.
-How you doing?
-[gasps] Oh my God.
How you doing?
Are you the mother of Stella?
This is Scarlett, mother of Stella.
You're doing a great job. And your name?
-Chris. Good to meet you.
-Chris.
Stella made all this happen.
I was walking by, talking into the camera,
and she was the only one out and about
and she was very friendly.
What are your thoughts on the city?
It's a city with, like,
the greatest soul in the world.
We have our problems, for sure.
And there's a ton of inequity
and all of that.
But we've lived here…
I moved here in 2001.
-Okay.
I haven't ever experienced violent crime.
I don't live in fear.
Like, the media will
make you feel like
it's the scariest place in the world.
-Right.
They sort of fester on Memphis, don't they?
I raised my children
right here in the middle.
They run the streets and ride their bikes
and do all the things.
And we don't live in fear here.
It's just such a misconception.
-Little Rock, another one of those cities.
I was actually surprised.
It was nicer than I thought.
-Yeah.
And all of these places,
it depends where you are in the city.
-That's right.
-And I totally recognize that.
Like, we're, you know, very blessed.
But it's just a cool, cool city.
Yeah.
-Thank you, guys.
-My little daughter making it happen.
-Stella, you made it happen.
Thank you. You're welcome to Memphis.
Tom, I just hope you continue to misbehave.
What else is there to do?
[laughter]
[Bill] This is another cool Memphis area.
It's called Overton Park.
-It just keeps going?
-Yeah.
-Bill, this is…
-Another lovely midtown neighborhood.
What's interesting about this neighborhood
is John Overton was
a well-known Memphis conservationist.
He created Overton Park.
Which has now been given to the city.
And it's a municipal golf course
and a big open green space area
and an untouched forest
right in the middle of the city
that butts up to the Memphis Zoo.
And why I'm saying this is
another thing that people
just don't know about Memphis is
our zoo has been ranked
the number one zoo in the country
many years, different years.
Who would think that in Memphis, right?
-I wouldn't think any of this
in Memphis, to be honest.
-Well, there's a lot to our city.
This massive Gothic building
was the Sears Tower in Memphis.
That was really the precursor to Amazon.
Back when Sears and Roebuck had catalogs,
floors and floors and floors of people
taking all the catalog orders
and shipping them.
And this building, the perspective
that you're getting right now…
-See how far back it goes?
-Oh, yeah. Way back there.
It's massive.
-So, you're talking nationwide?
Nationwide. This was the catalog…
So, how did it work? People would actually
send a letter with what they wanted?
-Did you ever see a Sears catalog?
-No.
Okay, so a Sears catalog
was just like a phone book,
except it was glossy paper.
If you ever went in a Sears, you could buy
anything from a craftsman wrench
to a pair of underwear,
to a vacuum cleaner,
to an icebox,
to a pair of women's shoes in a Sears.
-Hmm.
The catalog had every single item
they ever carried in it.
And if you lived off
in a rural area somewhere,
everybody had a Sears catalog,
and you would call Sears up and order it.
So, you had floors and floors and floors
of people answering the phone,
taking orders, processing the orders,
and getting it shipped to you.
About 20 years ago…
look how big the son of a b*tch is.
-Look. It's huge.
-It just keeps going. Yeah.
About 15, 20 years ago,
when Amazon took over
that kind of business,
Sears shut down
the whole Sears catalog thing.
And this place was shut down, boarded up,
and there was not
a single human being in it for 20 years.
And here we are in Midtown, Memphis
with this massive property here.
As you can imagine, just like Chicago,
all of the neighborhood
around here was blighted.
-Everyone was working here.
Because all the business went away.
Some developers got together
and repurposed it.
So, now this building has in it,
office buildings,
it's got a high school in it.
It's got restaurants in it.
It's got everything in it.
And it has the largest
not-for-profit doctor's office
called Church Health Center
that is specifically for the working poor.
You, inside this place,
in the Church Health Center
on the backside,
can get world-class primary care.
-Free?
-Free.
-Or cheap?
[Peter] Love it when things are done
in just such cool styles.
Something as boring as
a parking garage looks cool.
-How are you ladies doing?
-You gonna take our picture?
I'm doing a video on Memphis.
Can I ask you a question?
-Sure.
-How is this place?
-Crosstown?
-Yeah.
-It's awesome.
-It's awesome?
Definitely look inside.
And do all ladies
style like you here in Memphis?
[laughter]
You're styling.
-How's the city?
-It's great.
-You love it?
Don't listen to the media
when they say, you know…
-Memphis is great.
-Okay.
-It's firing on all cylinders right now?
-Mm-hmm.
Good music, food, culture?
-Oh, definitely.
-Of course.
Okay, cool.
Barbecue. Get some barbecue.
-Better than Texas?
-[scoffs]
-[Bill] Because it is.  Everybody knows.
-Hands down.
And here's the thing.
In Texas, they make brisket,
which is beef.
Don't you know you're supposed to
grill beef and barbecue pork?
-They got it all backwards.
-[giggling]
-See what I'm saying?
-Mm-hmm.
-There's a science behind it.
-There is a science behind it.
Bill's on his phone, which means
he's putting something together.
I'm getting in touch with the guy
who runs this show.
-No way. Nice.
-Check it out.
-Wow!
-Look at that.
-Yeah.
They purposely left
a lot of the original stuff
as an homage to what it once was.
This is the graduating class
of the high school that's in here,
Crosstown High School.
-This is Todd.
-Todd. Nice to meet you.
-I guess you manage this place.
-I do.
-And he's one of the co-founders.
-For better or worse.
So he was one of the guys
that took this building
from an abandoned Sears and made it this.
[Todd] Built in 1927,
1.5 million square feet.
-Wow.
-So 25 football fields of space.
The building's so long that if you
were to turn it kind of on its head,
that that ends at the top.
It'd be 200 feet taller
than the Chrysler Building in New York.
The way it works is
it's basically a vertical city.
The ground floor is an old town square.
Yep.
You've got six restaurants, grocery,
coffee obviously, ice cream, pharmacy,
hair salon, nail salon, bank branch, etc.
We have 72 tenants total,
half of which are nonprofits
doing important work around Memphis.
But arts and music is the spark.
It's the lifeblood of the building.
The owner of the building
had a vision back in 2010.
It had been empty for over 20 years
by the time we got started.
And so it was just a daunting task
with so much…
-I can't imagine.
-…space, and it was the recession.
So who's investing this much money?
Believes this much in the city?
-Because this is a huge reno.
-It's massive, yeah.
Over 30 different sources of funding
came together.
-Okay. Mostly local?
-So mostly local.
We used new market tax credits,
federal incentives to encourage
development in low-income census tracts.
And then historic tax credits
that are federal incentives
to incentivize rehabbing old buildings.
-Are both parties pushing those?
-Seems like it. Yeah.
-Okay.
It seems like it.
How you doing?
-This is the Memphis Listening Lab.
-Oh, nice.
So I always say if Crosstown's a
vertical city, this is our public library.
But because it's Memphis,
it's music instead of books.
So a guy named John King,
he would have been 83 I think this year,
passed away a few years ago.
-But he collected, 50,000 albums.
-Wow.
So you can figure out what
you're interested in, tell the folks here,
they'll pull the album, and then
you come back to the listening stations.
-Oh, nice.
-You just look out on the city and chill.
-Chill.
There's high school classes,
music appreciation classes in here.
-This is cool. I've never seen this.
Yeah. It's pretty amazing.
[Bill] It's a library for vinyl.
-You guys from here?
-I'm from Mississippi.
I'm from St. Louis,
but I grew up mostly here.
-Okay. What city do you like better?
Oh, I would say I like Memphis better.
-Okay.
-What about you?
Mississippi, man.
I'm a hometown man, but Memphis
does have some great things here.
-Okay. How's it working at this place?
It's amazing. It's like a dream come true.
-You love vinyl?
-Oh, music major.
-Yeah.
So probably one of the best places to be.
-Yeah. This is my heaven.
-This is your heaven.
Someone comes in here,
like, I want whatever record.
-You're going up on the ladder?
-Yeah.
That is so cool, man.
Behind that door is Southern Grooves
Recording Studio,
and down the hall
is the headquarters of WYXR,
so we have our own radio station as well.
Okay, nice.
So you've got broadcast,
you've got Memphis Listening Lab education,
you've got a recording studio next door.
Crosstown Arts has two performance venues,
so you've got performance, recording,
production, education, broadcast.
All the people involved in the music-making
process all along the way,
and they come here.
-Is there stuff on every level?
-Yes, there are.
So, ground level
is all the restaurant retail.
Two through six are church help,
Crosstown Arts, the high school,
city leadership,
the 72 tenants that I mentioned.
Floor 7 through 10 are 265 apartments.
People are living here?
So, my family lives on the 10th floor,
my daughter goes to school on the 4th,
my office is on the 2nd.
-You're serious?
-I do not have a car.
-Your coffee shop's downstairs.
-That's right.
This is Crosstown Arts,
the contemporary arts center.
They have the performance venues,
gallery spaces, artist residency program,
and the maker space.
So, this is one of the music venues
called the Green Room.
It's a small music lounge.
-Hey, Alex.
-Hey, Todd.
-How are you?
-I'm good. How are you?
So, these guys, it's live music
three, four times a week.
-Oh, awesome.
-Everything from singer-songwriter,
to amazing jazz and blues,
and hip-hop and DJ,
all the genres.
I got to take you in here, Peter.
It's called Art Bar.
It's called Art Bar
because the top of the bar lifts up
and you install art pieces
that are then exhibited by artists.
And then this great cocktail menu.
We're now in the tower of the building
and it just keeps going back.
-So, nighttime this comes alive?
-Yeah, absolutely.
So, this is 5:00 to midnight
every day of the week except for Monday.
-So, not long ago, someone's in Mississippi
ordering some socks and a candle.
Right.
And someone's
putting that order together right here.
This neighborhood is flourishing
because of all the jobs.
Sears goes away, neighborhood goes down.
You guys have come in.
You're bringing back
something into the community.
Not gonna have the manufacturing jobs
as before, obviously.
-Right.
Well, when Sears was here,
there were 1,500 employees.
And funny enough,
there's 1,500 employees now.
-Seriously?
-In the 72 organizations.
-Oh, that's awesome.
-So, for 20 years, there was nothing.
And now, between the residents,
employees, students,
just people coming and going,
there's 3,000 people
coming and going every day.
-So, that must have helped
the neighborhood out a bit.
-Massively.
-Okay.
-Big time.
-Yeah.
-[Bill] This is how I remember it.
-So, y'all came in this front.
When we got started,
that's what it looked like.
-This is where we walked in this place.
-Right.
Wow.
-How much was this project, Todd?
About $220 million.
This is how it used to be,
orders would come in up on the 2nd floor.
They'd put them in
these pneumatic tubes to the upper floors.
They'd grab the goods,
put them down these huge spiral chutes
that went all 10 floors,
came down to a conveyor belt
that a the truck on the south side,
train on the north side.
This is the last day of the retail store
before it went out of business.
This is what it was in 2010
when we got started and where we are.
This is 1927.
Crazy fact, the original structure,
620,000 square feet in 1927.
They built that in 180 days.
Six months.
So, all these atria that you're seeing,
those were just floors.
-We cut all that out. We saw cut…
-Oh, no way.
-Yeah, so we…
-That was a floor?
Those were all floors.
We saw cut through three miles of concrete
and took out 52 million pounds
of concrete to create the atrium.
-All right. Guys…
-Come on out to the 10th floor balcony.
She's having a good time.
So, is that my daughter?
-Do you know her, Todd?
-I might know her.
Her name is Corinne Richardson.
She's 16, 10th grader at Crosstown High.
And she's just chilling out here.
-She's at Crosstown?
-She's not in school right now.
Let's see what time it is.
Oh, it's 3:47, so…
…AP testing.
-You what?
-AP testing.
AP testing. Okay.
I'm giving a little tour.
We're doing some video.
Say hi to Peter.
He only has 4.2 million followers.
Hi. Nice to meet you.
-How is it going to high school here?
-Awesome.
-You're loving it?
-It's so fun.
-You just go down the building?
-And I'm late every single day.
That's true. She takes the stairs
to high school every day.
-That's not bad.
-Literally wake up 5 minutes before class.
-I do.
Is your dad winning
the cool dad award of the year?
100% Yeah.
-Right answer. Right answer.
Ding, ding, ding.
-Killing it in this environment.
Oh, yeah. It's so fun.
Todd's 16-year-old daughter
still really likes him,
so that's an amazing accomplishment.
Yeah. Well, we still got
a little ways to go.
-[Bill] That's quite uncommon.
-Uh-huh.
So, are these rentals
or you're selling them?
-They're rentals.
-What's the rent like?
Market rate would be for a two-bedroom,
1,200 square feet, around $2,000.
Okay.
The other cool thing is
Memphis Teacher Residency.
They recruit recent graduates to Memphis.
They earn a tuition-free
master's in education.
in return for teaching in Memphis'
highest-need urban schools
for three years after that.
And so, their training is here,
but they also live in the building.
St. Jude rents 40 apartments
for their PhD visiting researchers.
And then Crosstown Arts has 12 apartments
for their artist residency.
So, of the 265, about 90 of them
are artists-in-residence,
teachers-in-residence,
and doctors-in-residence.
This is just a normal
one-bedroom apartment.
-You got to love these pillars here.
-Yeah.
And the ceiling height, it just…
It's really great.
-So, this would be
roughly two grand a month?
Um, about. Yeah.
-Oh, and you got a full balcony.
-Yeah. 10th floor.
-This is awesome.
Hey, good sir. How's it going?
-Question.
-Yeah.
Y'all covering the event tonight?
What y'all doing? Or organized?
These guys… Todd knows it,
but go in and talk to whoever's in there.
I don't know.
I'm just making a video on Memphis.
-You're an officer?
-Mm-hmm. Crime scene investigator.
How's it going?
It's Memphis.
-Which means?
If you're doing something on Memphis,
you want to know about the crime?
-I'm just…
-Local news.
Watch the local news?
It is exactly that.
Memphis has been in
the top five for a reason.
-But in a neighborhood like this
it feels pretty good.
Well, I mean, Midtown is an eclectic area.
So you've got
your good and your bad mixed together,
and artistic, funky kind of juxtaposition
with the location of the city
for what it is.
-But police officers
always see a different side of the city.
-Always.
-You guys are seeing the worst of it.
We're seeing people at their worst.
But crime's gone down a bit.
Homicides have gone down.
You can say that by the numbers,
but the numbers are still high.
Of the top ten,
Memphis is always in the top three.
Always.
-Thank you for your work, sir.
Without you guys
everything falls apart in two seconds.
Yeah. It probably would.
It would be lawless.
-Take care.
[Todd] Sorry, guys.
Excuse us. Sorry.
-Photo bomb. I apologize.
-I'm making the picture way uglier.
Yeah, yeah. You right.
[laughter]
[Bill] Lord knows
you don't want me in there.
[Todd] So I mentioned Crosstown Arts
is a contemporary arts center.
Basically what we do is try to provide
resources for artists and musicians
in Memphis to make their work
and to showcase their work.
So in galleries for visual arts
or music venues for music.
And in here is what they call shared art.
So it's a membership-based maker space.
-You can pay a monthly membership fee.
-Oh, nice.
You have access to screen printing,
large format printing,
laser cutter, digital media lab.
It has all the software for film
and music and photography editing.
And then sculptors and furniture makers
come in and have access
to this full professional wood shop.
Oh, wow.
The other thing I love is this glass leads
into the entrance into the high school.
So when they come into school,
they see all this happening.
-Do they have shop class at high school?
-They have their own.
-They have their own version of this.
-Oh, wow.
I like to call them 901.
That's our area code.
-What's up? Juan?
-Meet Peter.
-Peter. Nice to meet you.
You're running
different ethnic cuisines every day.
Yeah. We've got a lot every day.
But we do have from Mexico,
Venezuela, and Sudan.
We've had people from just about
any country you can imagine.
Burundi, Bhutan, Pakistan.
You got Ukraine. You have Borscht?
-We've had employees from Ukraine.
-Okay.
We also had a St. Jude patient
from Ukraine.
Came at 17, worked for us
while she went through chemotherapy.
-Wow.
-Had her leg amputated after 19 rounds.
But was cancer-free.
Completed her stint
without going back to Europe.
Got married
and brought the husband three months later.
[Todd] No way!
Remember what I was saying it's provided.
Working or you have to work 10, 11, 12.
How many hours?
10 hours a week. You have to work.
They provide quality health care
to the working uninsured.
This is where you would
come in to see a doctor or nurse.
You get primary care here.
If you need specialist care,
then they have partnerships.
Over 1,000 doctors and nurses
volunteer their time
with Church Help
to provide the care that the people need.
Okay. So I work 10 hours.
I need health care.
I'm getting it here no matter what?
You can come here. There's walk-in clinic.
And then you can also come here
and participate in their…
it's not insurance,
but it's their wellness care program.
Depending on demand, right,
there may be a little time to wait,
but you can get care.
-If I need an MRI…
-Yep.
So they will work with
Methodist University Hospital
or Baptist Hospital,
the two main hospital systems in Memphis
to get you what you need.
Scott's both a Methodist minister
and a doctor.
And he said, if you look at the life
of Jesus, he tells us to do three things.
Preach, teach, and heal.
Church doesn't get a pass on the third one.
Oh.
And so his big thing is that
this place is supported by churches
that actually don't take any federal money.
They'll take the state,
Medicaid things for children, et cetera,
but they support it all
through fundraising.
There's a teaching kitchen here where
they work with doctors and their patients
on eating and cooking healthily
because we know wellness
is not just about a prescription.
-Oh, yeah. That's important.
-You come here to
get your prescription,
but then you look up
and there's wellness being produced.
So there's a 25,000-square-foot
YMCA up there.
Right above us is a dental clinic.
What they found is one of the primary ways
somebody can increase their wage
is fixing their teeth.
And so they have a 32-chair dental clinic.
It's the largest nonprofit dental clinic
like it in the country.
-Great to meet you.
-Todd. Good work.
-All right, my friend.
-Todd, take care, man.
-Enjoy.
-I'm loving it.
He's about to find out
what barbecue bologna is.
[Peter] All right. This is the place.
Cozy Corner BBQ.
Now hiring.
-[woman 1] Enjoy.
-[woman 2] Okay. I will.
That dude right there is the founder.
Where are all the pictures?
All the pictures are gone.
But everybody that knows anything
about barbecue has eaten here.
Dignitaries, notables,
and it's been right here the whole time.
That guy's wife, who is now,
I think, in her 90s,
went to Manassas High School,
and they opened this restaurant
a long time ago,
the family still rubs it.
Okay. Walk us through this, Bill.
Barbecue Cornish hen.
Barbecue Bologna.
Ribs.
-Barbecue spaghetti.
-Never seen or heard of that.
It's because it's killer.
And pulled pork sandwich.
Barbecue spaghetti.
-It's got a little barbecue meat in it.
-Instead of pasta sauce, it's barbecue?
It's got pasta sauce and barbecue in it.
Little Italian influence here, Bill?
Little Italian barbecue influence.
Huh.
-Pretty good, isn't it?
-Yeah.
Yeah.
Barbecue Bologna.
-Okay.
-And it has slaw on it.
Just suck it up.
Just go for it.
And all you do is you pick it up
like a normal sandwich,
shove it in.
Stupid isn't it?
-I've never tasted that before.
-[Bill laughs]
All right.
Cornish hen, I'm gonna peel off this side.
It's smoked and then barbecued.
And I don't know how they do it.
But they keep it tender as cr*p.
So you just get in there
with the fingers, Indian style.
Just get in there. I'm eating
off this half. You eat off that half.
Just get in there and get you
a big old mess out like that and pop it.
Just pop?
I see why you're doing the fingers.
Just get it with your fingers, dude.
You're in Memphis.
You can't eat nice with this sh*t.
I got to put it right up here.
Bring someone from out of town
trying to eat  barbecue with a fork.
So that's what you want, right?
Just crisp skin.
Just all of it. Skin, everything in there.
All the flavors coming together for you.
-That's good.
-Yeah.
-I like that.
-And then a rib.
And they do their ribs
different than a lot.
They slow cook them
and do something with the barbecue.
-And get that charred on the outside.
-Okay.
But I'm a huge fan of this place's ribs.
Now, there are really good ribs
in Memphis and a lot of other places.
But these are unique
and a little different.
Been here forever.
God, it's so good.
You're gonna love the rib.
Smoky, crispy on the outside,
tender on the inside,
and then the sauce is killer.
How good is that?
-Wow.
-I know.
How do they cook that?
That's a really, really Memphis-y taste.
The smoke.
Tender, crispy on the outside,
and the sweet sauce all flavored together.
-Oh, yeah.
-That's a very typical Memphis rib taste.
Okay. How do they cook this?
-Just simmering forever?
-In the old smoke room back there.
They smoke stuff all night long.
And then the last one
is your pulled pork sandwich.
Why don't you bite that
and then tell me what you like the most.
I'm curious.
They just drip it in the barbecue.
They go abundance with the barbecue.
Yeah.
There we go.
-That pretty good?
-Mm-hmm.
That's good.
Mmm.
The sauce has some kick, you know?
Well, you've got the hot.
These are all normal.
But it's got a good kick. It's cool.
What do you like the most?
I'm not really a rib guy traditionally,
but I'd say the ribs.
-Really?
-And this.
That's a compliment
if you're not a rib guy.
Not really.
But I love a good sand-o.
And this is hitting.
My fingers are committed
and indented into this bun right now,
so I'm gonna stay here.
You're in now.
Bill, that was awesome.
Thank you. Appreciate it.
Listen, an honor to show off my town.
No, I can feel it. Love it.
And I want you guys to know Bill has
an awesome documentary, Undefeated.
I'm gonna leave the link down below.
-And also a podcast.
-Yeah.
Where you're getting a human story.
It's called An Army of Normal Folks.
It's based around this idea.
Government's proven woefully inadequate
in serving the least advantaged among us.
There's neighborhoods all over the place
that we drive by that we see
abject despair and loss,
and we don't want to have
our car break down there.
But as we cruise by and we look back down
that street or over that viaduct,
we think to ourselves, man,
somebody outta do something
about that one day.
-Honestly, I want to know who's somebody.
-Okay.
Maybe we need to kick
that rearview mirror 15 degrees to the left
and say maybe I could do something
about that one day.
And I don't think
the smart people on Fox and CNN,
and I don't think
the smart people in DC and LA
have fixed anything.
If anything, I think they're probably
incented by an enormous amount of power
to continue to craft
narratives that divide us.
They're not helping anything.
And I think the anecdote
to all of what's ailing us
is an army of normal folks.
Guys like you and me saying,
hey, here's what I'm good at.
Here's what I'm passionate about.
Here's an area of need in my community.
Why don't I just engage
and try to help one person?
And if we had millions of people
across our country doing that,
literally an army of normal folks
engaging where they can, how they can,
I think we could change a lot what ails us.
And so the podcast tells stories
of people doing that very thing.
-Good stuff, Bill.
-Yeah, this was fun.
Guys, thanks for coming along
on that journey.
Until the next one.
[jazz music]